hello I'm your host David Bernard
today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in Revenue
cat state of subscription apps report
each episode in this series will explore
one crucial metric and share actionable
insights from Top subscription app
operators with me today Rachel chakura
head of consumer product at the weather
company on the podcast I talk with
Rachel about how to optimize paid
conversion the impact of external
factors on AB testing and why increasing
sub subscribers probably shouldn't be
your top priority hey Rachel thanks so
much for joining me on the podcast today
thank you so much for having me I'm
excited to have the conversation so
we're talking state of subscription apps
and one of the key metrics a lot of
people look at in the report to kind of
determine how their business is is
shaping up compared to others is the
trial conversion races like converting
from a free trial converting from App
open to paid and then ultimately that's
also converting from free premium to pay
and so that's what I wanted to kind of
focus on today was optimizing and like
strategy for how to think about those
things and the weather channel app is
interesting because you have both a very
generous pre tier which does kind of
make it more challenging to push that
subscription as opposed to kind of hard
pay walls or kind of apps that are more
aggressive or have fewer features but
they also have a free trial for the
premium features so it's kind of an
interesting model so let's just start
with that aspect of like balancing free
and having a free trial even for a
Premium app yeah absolutely so as you
pointed out our app is very generous
from an ad supported free experience and
that's because we've always seen
ourselves really as a utility whether is
in some ways a commodity that exists
throughout the ecosystem and so as we
look at the landscape we know that
there's a level of importance of having
a certain amount of information that is
just readily available for those core
user needs but what we have identified
is that there are users and specific
cohorts within our business that are
willing to pay and so we have over the
past four or five years established a
really strong premium experience in
which we're able to really play into the
user need of specific cohorts and in our
case it really is that weather
Enthusiast that is a power user wants
access to more data more sophisticated
radar experience and that has allowed us
to at least Drive the initial growth of
the business there's still a lot of
value that core users are getting from
us and so as we look to unlock the next
phase of growth we are looking at what
is available overall and how do we
better balance the gate that exists
within the product to get users into
that funnel I think that's a really
great frame of reference to start
thinking about subscriber conversion in
that so many apps are so focused on
getting that subscriber that they're not
seeing the forest for the trees of there
being so many cohorts that would be
casual users that they could still
monetize via ads and maybe nurture over
time to become a subscriber and so it's
interesting on the fact that as a
business the weather channel has chosen
to give away more value for free and
then understanding who very specifically
is the cohort that is willing to pay
more and then monetizing those better
like what's the process for a better
understanding who those people are are
and then better targeting them so you
can keep those free users but then still
have this like extra value you layer on
we do a lot of research we know a lot
about our users and about our business
and the industry so everything that we
do and construct in a subscription
product and a core product is centered
around those core jobs to be done of our
users and that comes through research it
also comes through analytics we take all
the data that we know about a user and
create cohort and segmentation that
allows us to better super serve those
users with the data and the information
and the features that they care most
about and are willing to pay for so in
this model it's been really wonderful to
be able to look at what our power users
care about because a lot of those
weather enthusiasts are power users for
us and so they spend almost every day
multiple times a day in the product
they've been with us through the legacy
of our brand and so there's a lot that
we can lean into there but what's going
to be really important for the next
phase of growth because the subscription
industry at at large is going through an
evolution right now as are we is to find
that next segment that we can lean into
build features for and move past just
core weather data as a value behind the
pay wall into the what's next that's
additive to that user experience in
finding those new segments and unlocking
those new opportunities
what are the tools or what's the process
you're using to discover those things we
do interviews with our users we do broad
surveys to understand user need and
behaviors we look at product analytics
we look at subscription analytics
through things like Revenue cat that
enable us to identify those new
opportunities so what it allows us to do
is look at the behaviors themselves look
at what users are saying are the
behaviors or the needs that they have
and really matching that up to what
they're doing when they are in the
product to make sure that those things
align because not always do user need
that is verbally communicated actually
match the behavior that you see in the
product and then looking at really where
those drop off points are all the way
from acquisition throughout the
experience throughout the subscription
life cycle that we can better serve them
and lean into those moments that matter
so are you starting to segment and build
up kind of an understanding of an
individual user and then hitting them
with a a more specific and targeted pay
wall or pointing them to specific areas
of the product that you know is then
going to help nudge them towards
conversion absolutely on both fronts so
we have historically been a very
Anonymous based site we get a lot of
traffic through the Google searches and
going back to kind of how we perceived
ourselves as a utility brand really
didn't require our user to have a
significant value exchange with us for a
long time such as providing an email
address so that we know who you are and
what you care about as that begins to
evolve then we're able to lean into
improved targeting and understanding how
best to package the subscription product
how best to actually Elevate features
within the experience itself that is
most relevant and attractive to you to
encourage that buying Behavior we do use
AI propensity models and things like our
weather targeting that really enable us
to be more sophisticated in our
marketing without even having to
consider as much the user side of things
but we can take the context because
weather is such a contextual signal that
adds value to the acquisition and the
conversion of that user into being a
subscriber what do you mean by
propensity models I don't know that our
audience will all be familiar with that
we use data science to actually
determine who is most likely to
subscribe or take an action within our
product so it takes a lot of the data
signals based on what you're doing in
the product what we know about you and
it merges those things together to give
us a signal as to whether or not you are
likely or unlikely to subscribe so many
apps are getting better and more
sophisticated at this as kind of the
tooling the industry and other things
have progressed and then as you know Ai
and machine learning and these models
have gotten better they can be such a
powerful tool when used well to drive
those outcomes for the audience it is
really important to continue to evaluate
and improve and refine those models
because I have also seen the other end
of the Spectrum in which we have created
a model and we believe it works very
well but if not tuned and properly
managed things change right economics
change competition changes and so you
really need to look at the effectiveness
of your models if that is something that
you are deploying in building those
propensity models and thinking about
converting folks from the premium
experience to the paid experience so
many big consumer apps pushing to
convert more of those free users to paid
there's maybe a bit of over monetization
that we've maybe gotten a little too
aggressive at times about hard pay walls
and and using every nudge tactic in the
Playbook how do you think about
balancing the subscriber conversion and
monetization against kind of the
customer experience of it all so the way
we look at it is that it is all centered
around the customer we don't lead with
the monetization to us that is an
outcome or an output of us really doing
a good job with creating a performant
and useful experience for our users we
lean heavily into research to understand
our users and their needs so that when
we think about how best to grow our
subscription product we do so within the
context of what a user really is looking
to achieve when they visit the weather
app or weather.com and how do we lean
into that behavior and that need in
order to have a very clear value
exchange and to surface the subscription
at a moment that really matters and so
thinking about that customer journey is
essential I'll give you an example one
of the things that works really well for
us is our radar experience so leaning
into that Persona that we are hypers
serving they like to look at data and
make their own conclusions about the
data and so that is why we've leaned
heavily into things like access to more
data like the hourly details or even
more radar information and so what we
have found is that by really giving
context and creating these moments of
delight and access points that really
start to drive demand are just hard to
refute because they're core to the
experience they the user themselves they
are finding value and finding a need
that it allows us to better balance user
experience and monetization we do know
that if we tip that pendulum too far in
One Direction it doesn't work well for
us and it doesn't work well for a lot of
Brands and they you know it really is
about finding that right balance in the
tearing strategy yeah and you know for
for some apps they're going to choose it
and this is what's interesting about
having this conversation in the context
of the state of subscription apps report
is that when you look at the benchmarks
it's going across the entire industry
and so some apps do choose to monetize
more heavily and but then you just you
understand the trade-offs and I I think
it's really interesting how you're
framing these trade-offs because you do
value those freemium users more than a
lot of apps do and then as a company
your roots are in monetizing those free
users as well so like The Weather
Channel been ad supported for decades
and the app itself I believe it just
introduced subscriptions in the last
like two years so I think it's
interesting to hear you kind of talk
through these things in that broader
context is that so many apps make so
many different kinds of choices but this
is like a great way to build a really
big business is that you really take
care of your customers and you deliver a
lot of value to those free users and
then you build on top of that value to
then charge and you find great ways to
monetize those for users so that there
is like you keep saying a value exchange
so as you're thinking through all of
these things do you have any kind of
specific advice for folks to take away
of like in your day-to-day what are you
doing how are you thinking you know what
are the Tactical things you're doing to
help make these decisions and to guide
the business so our big Focus right now
is data and
experimentation so really creating a lot
more rigor in how do we test and learn
whether it's the change in a color of a
button or a the length of our trial for
example those are things that are really
essential in kind of growth hacking the
conversion rate and acquisition of new
subscribers and so we've been able to
improve our data position we've put a
lot of work into that to unlock our
ability to be a little bit more Nimble
and more data driven in the execution of
our acquisition strategy so that's where
we're focused right now and so we are
constantly re-evaluating full endtoend
experience and how do we just continue
to elevate that make it more performant
make it really a positive experience for
our users so that they continue to pay
use and see value in the exchange that
we have with them you mentioned testing
there what are your thoughts on like how
to best execute testing so that you come
to the right conclusions from the test
you run cuz I mean running something you
mentioned you know even testing button
colors which at the scale of the weather
channel is where you can actually start
to see some wins but you can also easily
fool yourself if you don't have it set
up so how do you think about kind of
being rigorous in your testing yeah I
think having a clear hypothesis to start
is really important as well as
welldefined key results so what are you
trying to achieve what kpi are you
looking to move the needle on and I
think one of the things that we have
found as a business because as you
mentioned we do have the ability to
scale experiments pretty quickly and so
while we can reach stat Sig on an
experiment within 24 hours in some cases
we do recognize that buying behavior is
often influenced by many other variables
out outside of very specific colors and
text right purchase Behavior could be
everything from what is the weather
outside what is my need right in that
moment that's going to drive the
purchase behavior and so we recognize
that and we know that we have to run
experiments for long enough to be able
to because it impacts our business see
what happens in certain weather
conditions to see what happens with all
these variables in mind to really make
sure that what we are seeing out of that
experiment is true and something that we
can believe and move forward yeah that's
a great way to think about it and I I
had even thought about how much not even
just with the weather app but but even
for straa or other apps you know if a
straa runs a test on a Wednesday that's
probably going to get way different
results than they did it on a Saturday
because more people are out biking and
hiking and doing the things it that yeah
it's something that we live and breathe
because in the weather business we often
use that as one of our privacy forward
signals because weather is actually a
really strong predictor in a user action
it's funny we just recently went through
a lot of marketing research and one of
the things that came up is that weather
is an original influencer because it is
an influencer of users behavior and so
we know that very well and one thing
that we con L remind ourselves is we
have to do what we know works and what
we understand about user Behavior user
psychology and things like weather's
influence on that and so we really do
try to take that into account as we make
these decisions run the tests and put
new products in Market awesome well
Rachel it has been so much fun chatting
through all of this with you so many
great insights for folks to take away as
we wrap up is there anything you wanted
to share we're going to share some links
in the show notes but anything you
wanted to say as we wrap up I just will
say the subscription business the
subscription industry at large is
undergoing yet another change and I
think it's really important for all of
us as peers anybody who is in that part
of the business to lean on each other
because we are all going through very
similar things and while our industry is
may be different the experiences that
we're having with driving growth in a
subscription business is the same and we
should be able to create moments to lean
on each other and share notes because
it'll make us all more effective as well
in the end awesome well thanks for doing
exactly that today by sharing what
you're learning at The Weather Channel
yeah thank you for having
me thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private community